Guide to the North Carolina Farm Bureau Records
North Carolina Farm Bureau Records
1936 - 1999
1936 1999
MC 00313
The bulk of these papers document the corporate activities of the North Carolina Farm Bureau between 1936 and 1999. The North Carolina Farm Bureau Federation, North Carolina Farm Bureau Mutual Insurance Company, North Carolina Farm Bureau Service Company, and North Carolina Farm Bureau Marketing Association are all represented in the documents of this collection. Also, a substantial amount of material testifies to the activities of the North Carolina Farm Bureau Women's Committee. Formats include correspondence, corporate documents, publications, financial ledgers, legal documents and transcripts, scrapbooks, photographs, film reels, audio recordings, and miscellaneous artifacts.
Organized in 1936 as a chapter of the American Farm Bureau, the North Carolina Farm Bureau was created to be a grassroots organization that would give farmers a unified voice on agricultural issues. Its Women's Committee was established in 1942. In 1953, the North Carolina Farm Bureau Mutual Insurance Company was established. Beginning in 1962, the North Carolina Farm Bureau pioneered creation of a group purchase program that was managed by the North Carolina Farm Bureau Service Company. The following year, the North Carolina Farm Bureau further expanded with the establishment of the North Carolina Farm Bureau Marketing Association. Because of the organization's involvement in legal and legislative matters, a Legal Foundation for the North Carolina Farm Bureau was created in 1983. In 1987, a Political Action Committee was also added. Educational programs of the Farm Bureau include the R. Flake Shaw Memorial Scholarship Fund, the Institute for Future Agricultural Leaders, and "Agriculture in the Classroom."
54.5 linear feet
North Carolina State University Libraries, Special Collections Research Center
Gifts from the Farm Bureau, May 2001 and June 2002.
Gifts from the North Carolina Farm Bureau, May, 2001 and June 2002.
The collection is divided into twelve series: Correspondence provides information on the Farm Bureau's relationship with county chapters of the organization, individual members, other state Farm Bureaus, and the American Farm Bureau Federation;Speeches and Statements made by Farm Bureau administrators;Organizational Documents for all of the five major divisions of the North Carolina Farm Bureau;Printed materials circulated by the North Carolina Farm Bureau and its major divisions, including handbooks, policies, reports, and pamphlets;Annual Meetings and Conferences contains materials relating to and collected at the organization's yearly conferences;Legal and Legislative Papers;Financial Materials;Reference Materials and Reports contains the various federal, state, corporate and non-profit resources used by the Farm Bureau for corporate research and political action research;Photograph series contains black and white prints of various people and buildings tied to the North Carolina Farm Bureau as well as two scrapbooks compiled by the organization for the years 1958 through 1960;Audiovisual series is comprised of film reels and recordings made by the Farm Bureau and utilized to present the organization's viewpoint on a certain agricultural issue;Artifacts collected by the North Carolina Farm Bureau;Additions.
Organized in 1936 as a chapter of the American Farm Bureau, the North Carolina Farm Bureau was created to be a grassroots organization that would give farmers a unified voice on agricultural issues. Its Women's Committee was established in 1942. In 1953, the North Carolina Farm Bureau Mutual Insurance Company was established. Beginning in 1962, the North Carolina Farm Bureau pioneered creation of a group purchase program that was managed by the North Carolina Farm Bureau Service Company. The following year, the North Carolina Farm Bureau further expanded with the establishment of the North Carolina Farm Bureau Marketing Association. Because of the organization's involvement in legal and legislative matters, a Legal Foundation for the North Carolina Farm Bureau was created in 1983. In 1987, a Political Action Committee was also added. Educational programs of the Farm Bureau include the R. Flake Shaw Memorial Scholarship Fund, the Institute for Future Agricultural Leaders, and "Agriculture in the Classroom."
During the height of the Great Depression, a group of North Carolina farmers traveled to Washington in order to seek a solution to their many economic problems. They became aware of a need for mass organization through which they could work together to solve some of their problems. After researching the farming organizations of the time, these farmers decided to create a North Carolina chapter of the American Farm Bureau.
On March 2, 1936, the first meeting of the North Carolina Farm Bureau was called to order by Chairman J. E. Winslow. Although this initial meeting was held in Greenville, North Carolina, the organization elected to establish its headquarters at 403 Evans Street in Greensboro. An original membership numbered slightly over 2,000 people and represented 24 counties in eastern North Carolina. At the time, membership dues were $2.00 per member. In July 1936, the North Carolina Farm Bureau held its first annual meeting in Raleigh on the campus of North Carolina State College. By the time of this meeting, membership had grown to 4,490 members from 30 counties.
Throughout the 1940s, membership in the North Carolina Farm Bureau continued to grow. By 1944, the organization had 30,000 members, thus fulfilling the quota set by the American Farm Bureau Federation. By the end of the decade, the North Carolina Farm Bureau led the South in membership statistics. Administrators also furthered participation by establishing a Women's Committee for the organization in 1942.
In 1953, the North Carolina Farm Bureau Mutual Insurance Company was established. The initial offering was limited to casualty lines. However, by the next year, members could receive life and annuity insurance through Southern Farm Bureau Life. Later additions to the insurance programs authorized fire lines and crop insurance. Later in the 1950s, the Farm Bureau elected to move its headquarters to Raleigh, where they inhabited the former Raleigh Times building.
Under the guidance of President B.C. Mangum, in 1962, the North Carolina Farm Bureau pioneered the creation of a group purchase program that would soon be adopted by other Farm Bureau chapters across the country. Managed by the newly-formed North Carolina Farm Bureau Service Company, this program offered a variety of Safemark products, including tires and batteries, to Bureau members at a substantial discount.
The following year, the North Carolina Farm Bureau furthered its expansion with the establishment of the North Carolina Farm Bureau Marketing Association. Involved in a number of commodity programs since its inception, the association provided farmers with the opportunity to strengthen both their marketing and bargaining powers. The initial focus of this sector was the hog market, however, markets for dairy products, broiler hens, and a variety of fruits and vegetables have also enjoyed success as a result of this program.
The 1970s proved to be another decade of growth for the Farm Bureau. The organization outgrew its initial Raleigh headquarters, and in 1971, moved to its current location on Glenwood Avenue. Later construction in 1980 and 1992 would even further expand this location. By 1974, membership had expanded to over 100,000 members.
Because of the organization's great involvement in legal and legislative matters, a Legal Foundation for the North Carolina Farm Bureau was created in 1983. In 1987, a Political Action Committee was also added. Recently, the Farm Bureau has established several programs that serve the educational needs of young people interested in a career in agriculture. Since 1958, the Farm Bureau has provided financial assistance to agriculture students through the R. Flake Shaw Memorial Scholarship Fund. In 1984, the North Carolina Farm Bureau, in conjunction with North Carolina State University, launched the Institute for Future Agricultural Leaders, which offers high school students the opportunity to attend a summer seminar on the prospects of a career in agriculture. The organization also soon added an "Agriculture in the Classroom" program that integrates ag-related curriculum into traditional courses of study.
The bulk of these papers document the corporate activities of the North Carolina Farm Bureau between 1936 and 1999. The North Carolina Farm Bureau Federation, North Carolina Farm Bureau Mutual Insurance Company, North Carolina Farm Bureau Service Company, and North Carolina Farm Bureau Marketing Association are all represented in the documents of this collection. Also, a substantial amount of material testifies to the activities of the North Carolina Farm Bureau Women's Committee. Formats include correspondence, corporate documents, publications, financial ledgers, legal documents and transcripts, scrapbooks, photographs, film reels, audio recordings, and miscellaneous artifacts.
North Carolina Farm Bureau Federation, Inc.; North Carolina Farm Bureau Marketing Association; North Carolina Farm Bureau Mutual Insurance Company; North Carolina Farm Bureau Service Company; North Carolina Farm Bureau Women's Committee; North Carolina Agriculture; Rural conditions North Carolina; North Carolina Agricultural insurance; North Carolina Women in agriculture; North Carolina Agricultural laws and legislation; Farm produce Marketing; North Carolina Societies, etc. Agriculture; Brochures; North Carolina Agriculture and politics; Financial statements; Speeches; Scrapbooks; Photographs; Videocassettes; Lecture notes; Letters (correspondence); Societies, etc. United States Agriculture; Filmstrips; Audiotapes
- Correspondence, 1947-1992; 2.5 linear feet
  Correspondence contained in this collection details the everyday activities and concerns of the North Carolina Farm Bureau. The earliest letters date back to 1947; however, the majority of the correspondence in this collection dates from the 1970s and 1980s. Letters from 1954 to 1966 were not acessioned with this collection, and all 1968 correspondence was reported missing by the Farm Bureau in October of 1985. Much of the correspondence includes letters from the president of the North Carolina Farm Bureau Federation to county chapters, individual members, and state polticians requesting support on a particular legislative issue. The series also contains a number of letters from other state farm bureaus and the American Farm Bureau Federation. Correspondence from the insurance, marketing, and service divisions are also included.
  - 1947-1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - January, 1953 - May, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - June, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - July, 1953 - September, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - October, 1953 - December, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - January, 1967 - December, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - January, 1969 - December, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - January, 1970 - June, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - July, 1970 - December, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - January, 1971 - June, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - July, 1971 - December, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - January, 1972 - June, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - July, 1972 - December, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - January, 1973 - December, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - January, 1974 - June, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - July, 1974 - December, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - January, 1975 - March, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - April, 1975 - June, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - July, 1975 - September, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - October, 1975 - December, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - January, 1976 - June, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - July, 1976 - September, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - October, 1976 - December, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - January, 1977 - March, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - April, 1977 - June, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - July, 1977 - September, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - October, 1977 - December, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - January, 1978 - March, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - April, 1978 - June, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - July, 1978 - December, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - January, 1979 - June, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - July, 1979 - September, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - October, 1979 - December, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - January, 1980 - March, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - April, 1980 - June, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - July, 1980 - September, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - October, 1980 - December, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - January, 1981 - December, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - January, 1982 - December, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - January, 1983 - June, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - July, 1983 - December, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - January, 1984 - December, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - January, 1985 - June, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - July, 1985 - September, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - October, 1985 - December, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - January, 1986 - December, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - January, 1987 - December, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - January, 1988 - December, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - January, 1989 - December, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - January, 1990 - December, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - January, 1991 - June, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - July, 1991 - December, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - January, 1992 - June, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - July, 1992 - September, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - October, 1992 - November, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - December, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - January, 1993 - March, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - April, 1993 - June, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - July, 1993 - August, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - September, 1993 - October, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - November, 1993 - December, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - January, 1994 - February, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - March, 1994 - April, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - May, 1994 - June, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - July, 1994 - August, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - September, 1994 - October, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - November, 1994 - December, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - January, 1995 - June, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - July, 1995 - December, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - January, 1996 - March, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - April, 1996 - June, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - July, 1996 - December, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - January, 1997 - June, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - January, 1998 - June, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - July, 1997 - December, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - July, 1998 - December, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Speeches and Statements, 1952-1993; 1.5 linear feet
  The three boxes in this series include speeches made by North Carolina Farm Bureau administrators at local and national Farm Bureau-sponsored events, as well as statements issued by the organization in reference to a certain legislative issue. The statements usually refer to national petitions and were read by a North Carolina Farm Bureau representative in Washington. Although some speeches and statements from the 1950s and 1960s are represented in this collection, documents from the 1970s and 1980s are dominant. Issues represented in this series range from local concerns over the dairy industry in North Carolina, to national legislation on tobacco and the taxation of cigarettes.
  - 1952-1953 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - 1967 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - 1969-1970 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - 1971 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - January, 1972 - April, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - May, 1972 - December, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - January, 1973 - May, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - June, 1973 - December, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - January, 1974 - June, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - July, 1974 - December, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - January, 1975 - May, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - June, 1975 - December, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - January, 1976 - March, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - April, 1976 - July, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - August, 1976 - December, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - January, 1977 - April, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - May, 1977 - August, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - September, 1977 - December, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - 1978 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - January, 1979 - June, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - July, 1979 - December, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - 1980 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - 1981 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - January, 1982 - March, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - April, 1982 - June, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - July, 1982 - December, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - January, 1983 - March, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - April, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - April, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - May, 1983 - September, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - October, 1983 - December, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - 1984 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - January, 1985 - June, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - July, 1985 - December, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - 1986 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - 1987 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - 1988 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - 1989 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - January, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - January, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - February, 1990 - December, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - 1991 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - 1993 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Organizational Documents, 1936-1999; 4 linear feet
  One of the largest series of the collection, organizational documents details a wide array of corporate activities undertaken by the North Carolina Farm Bureau. This series is divided into five main subseries, each of which represent the main division of the Farm Bureau. The first and largest of these is the North Carolina Farm Bureau Federation. Within this subseries, historical and biographical sketches of the organization and its leaders are provided. Also included is basic information regarding committees, membership statistics, and awards programs. The next subseries gives a basic overview of the creation and objectives of the North Carolina Farm Bureau Mutual Insurance Company. Third, a chronological arrangement of County Participation in the TBA Program provides insight into the inner workings of the North Carolina Farm Bureau Service Company. The next subseries focuses on the North Carolina Farm Bureau Marketing Association. In this subseries, each of the marketing programs, which range from hog marketing to dairy marketing, are listed and foldered individually. Finally, a complete listing of the minutes and other corporate documents of the North Carolina Farm Bureau Women's Committee are provided in the last subseries.
  - North Carolina Farm Bureau Federation
    - Organizational History
      - General Information, Philosophy, and Structure (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Historical Narratives (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - Constitution and Bylaws (Box 9, Folder 3)
      - Inaugural Year (1936) Meeting Minutes (Box 9, Folder 4)
      - Expansion of Programs (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - Newspaper Clippings (Box 9, Folder 6)
      - Farm Bureau Buildings (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Administration
      - A.C. Edwards- Biography (Box 9, Folder 8)
      - Gordon Maddrey- Biography (Box 9, Folder 9)
      - B.C. Magnum- Biography, 1970s (Box 9, Folder 10)
      - B.C. Magnum- Biography, 1980s (Box 9, Folder 11)
      - R. Flake Shaw- Biography (Box 9, Folder 12)
      - P.N. Taylor- Biography (Box 9, Folder 13)
      - J.E. Winslow- Biography (Box 9, Folder 14)
      - Election of Directors, 1967 - 1979 (Box 9, Folder 15)
      - County Presidents, 1979 - 1990 (Box 9, Folder 16)
      - Field Representatives (Box 9, Folder 17)
      - Personnel Policies (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Committees
      - Ag Nursery Committee (Box 9, Folder 19)
      - Aquaculture Committee (Box 9, Folder 20)
      - Beef Cattle Committee (Box 9, Folder 21)
      - Beef Cattle Committee (Box 9, Folder 22)
      - Beekeepers Committee (Box 9, Folder 23)
      - Bylaws, Finances, and Structure Committee (Box 9, Folder 24)
      - Cotton Advisory Committee (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Cotton Advisory Committee (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Dairy Advisory Committee (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - Economic Services Committee (Box 10, Folder 4)
      - Equine Committee (Box 10, Folder 5)
      - Equine Committee (Box 10, Folder 6)
      - Executive Committee, 1990-2002 (Box 113, Folder 4)
      - Field Crops Committee (Box 10, Folder 7)
      - Field Crops Committee (Box 10, Folder 8)
      - Forestry Committee (Box 10, Folder 9)
      - Fruit and Vegetables Committee (Box 10, Folder 10)
      - Marketing Programs Committee (Box 10, Folder 11)
      - Members and Programs Committee (Box 10, Folder 12)
      - Parking Committee (Box 10, Folder 13)
      - Peanut Advisory Committee (Box 10, Folder 14)
      - Peanut Advisory Committee (Box 10, Folder 15)
      - Political Action Committee (Box 10, Folder 16)
      - Poultry Committee (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - Poultry Committee (Box 11, Folder 2)
      - Scholarship Committee (Box 11, Folder 3)
      - Scholarship Committee, 1987-2010 (Box 113, Folder 5)
      - Space and Facility Needs Committee (Box 11, Folder 4)
      - Swine Committee (Box 11, Folder 5)
      - Swine Committee (Box 11, Folder 6)
      - Tobacco Advisory Committees (Box 11, Folder 7)
      - Tobacco Advisory Committees (Box 11, Folder 8)
      - Tobacco Advisory Committees (Box 11, Folder 9)
      - Tobacco Advisory Committees (Box 11, Folder 10)
      - Tobacco Advisory Committees (Box 11, Folder 11)
      - Young Farmer and Rancher Committee Minutes, 2008-2010 (Box 113, Folder 7)
      - Young Farmer and Rancher Committee (Box 11, Folder 12)
      - Miscellaneous Committees, 1953 - 1985 (Box 11, Folder 13)
      - Miscellaneous Committees, 1985 - 1990 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Membership Information
      - Membership Quotas (Box 11, Folder 15)
      - Membership Information, membership quotas, 1960-1991 (Box 114, Folder 7)
      - Membership Reports (Box 11, Folder 16)
      - Voting Delegate Strength (Box 11, Folder 17)
      - Membership Information, biographical form (Box 114, Folder 6)
    - Awards
      - Service Awards (Box 11, Folder 18)
      - Miscellaneous Awards (Box 11, Folder 19)
      - Annual Activities and Accomplishments (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - Miscellaneous Organizational Documents
      - 1971 - 1973 (Box 11, Folder 21)
      - 1974 - 1977 (Box 11, Folder 22)
  - North Carolina Farm Bureau Mutual Insurance Company
    - General Information (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Reports on Creation of Insurance Company (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Incorporation Documents (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Officers and Directors (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - NCFB Mutual Insurance Company, officers and directors, 1990-2002 (Box 114, Folder 8)
    - Personnel Policies (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - North Carolina Farm Bureau Service Company
    - General Information (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - TBA Service-to-Member Program Information (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - TBA Program County Participation, 1970 - 1971 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - TBA Program County Participation, 1975 - 1976 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - TBA Program County Participation, 1977 - 1978 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - TBA Program County Participation, 1979 - 1980 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - TBA Program County Participation, 1981 - 1982 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - TBA Program County Participation, 1983 - 1984 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - TBA Program County Participation, 1985 - 1991 (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - TBA Program Analyses (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - North Carolina Farm Bureau Marketing Association
    - General Information (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Hog Marketing Program, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Hog Marketing Program, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Hog Marketing Program, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Hog Marketing Program, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Hog Marketing Program, 1970 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Hog Marketing Program, 1971 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Hog Marketing Program, 1972 - 1975 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Hog Marketing Program, 1976 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Hog Marketing Program, 1983-1984 (Box 13, Folder 10)